Miriam Butterworth Papers 2008.0060
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Miriam Butterworth Papers
1935-2011
2008.0060
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
5.0 Linear feet
The collection contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, notes, photographs, artifacts, and memoirs regarding Miriam Butterworth's life and activism, as well as her participation in local, state, and national politics.
Miriam Butterworth
Biography
Miriam Brooks Butterworth, educator and political activist, was born on April 14, 1918. She graduated from Chaffee School in 1936 and received a Bachelors Degree from Connecticut College for Women in 1940 and a Masters Degree in 1959 from Wesleyan University in 1959. She married Oliver Butterworth in 1940; they raised four children together. Her experience studying in Nazi Germany in 1938 inspired Mrs. Butterworth to live a life of public service and political activism. She began her professional career as a teacher and later became active in many different political movements, including presidential campaigns, senatorial campaigns, the Freeze campaign to stop the production of nuclear arms, and various movements to increase the general public's voice in politics. She has served as a Eugene McCarthy delegate at the 1968 Democratic National Convention,; PUCA commissioner,; the West Hartford Town Council member, temporary president of Hartford College for Women, and West Hartford, Connecticut town historian.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, clippings, notes, photographs, artifacts, and memoirs regarding Miriam Butterworth's life and activism in local, state, and national campaigns from 1935-2008. Topics include Mrs. Butterworth's life, her career in education, Squam Lake, New Hampshire, and her political activism in presidential and senatorial campaigns, anti-war movements, the Caucus of Connecticut Democrats (CCD),; the Sane/Freeze campaign against nuclear proliferation,; West Hartford Town Council, and the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (WILPF).
Arrangement
Series I: Personal Papers (1935-2008) contains correspondence, memoirs, notes, and newspaper and periodical clippings concerning Miriam Butterworth's life. Clippings and correspondence are arranged chronologically. Other documents are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series II: Subject Files (1963-2005) contains correspondence, clippings, and notes concerning Mrs. Butterworth's career in political activism. Clippings and correspondence are arranged chronologically. Other documents are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series III: Photographs (1962-2000) contains photographs arranged chronologically.
Series IV: Oversized Materials (1936-2005)contains oversized materials arranged alphabetically.
Acquisition Information
The Miriam Butterworth Papers were donated to Archives & Special Collections in 2008 by Miriam Butterworth.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut politics, as well as anti-war activism. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Butterworth, Miriam; Butterworth, Oliver; Caucus of Connecticut Democrats; Sane/Freeze; West Hartford Town Council; Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (WILPF); Activists-- Peace.; Activists-- United States-- Connecticut.; City Councils-- Connecticut-- West Hartford.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Maps.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Squam Lake, New Hampshire.; West Hartford (Conn.)-- Politics and government.; West Hartford, Conn.; Women politicians-- Connecticut-- Biography.
- Series I: Personal Papers, 1935-2008
  - Awards and Honors, 1959-2005 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Documents, n.d. (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Documents, 1968-2011 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Certificates and Diplomas, 1940-2005 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1975-2005 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Letters to the Editor, 1968-2004 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Memoir: "Don't Just Stand There, or Living in Interesting Times, Part I" (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Memoir: "Don't Just Stand There Part II: Family Matters" (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Memoir: "Don't Just Stand There Part III: What on Earth Did You Do? Careers and Causes" (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Memoir: "Don't Just Stand There Part IV: The Past is Prologue" (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Memoir: "Don't Just Stand There Part V: Epilogue" (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Memoir: "Squam: A Sense of Place", n.d. (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Personal, 1938-2008 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Butterworth vs. Dempsey Court Case, 1963-1966 (Box 2:, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Oliver Butterworth, 1963-1994 (Box 2:, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Latin America, 1984-2003 (Box 2:, Folder 15)
  - Notes, People's Delegation to the Paris Peace Talks, 1971 (Box 2:, Folder 16)
  - Notes, People's Delegation to the Paris Peace Talks, 1971 (Box 2:, Folder 17)
  - Notebooks, Nicaragua Elections, 1984 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
  - Notebooks, Latin America Trip, 1988 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
  - Notebooks, El Salvador and Nicaragua, 1991 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
  - Notebook, Liberation Theology, 1991 (Box 2:, Folder 21)
  - Notebook, Honduras, 1998 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
  - Notes, Peace Appeal Congress, 1999 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
  - Notebook, The Hague, 1999 (Box 3:, Folder 24)
  - Notes, Miscellaneous, 1969-1999 (Box 3:, Folder 25)
  - Participant Booklet, Connecticut College Archeological Seminar in Israel and Jordan, 2000 (Box 3:, Folder 26)
  - Programs, 1935-2004 (Box 3:, Folder 27)
  - Speeches, n.d. (Box 3:, Folder 28)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1963-2005
  - Activism Files, 1962-2003 (Box 3:, Folder 29)
  - Caucus of Connecticut Democrats, 1969-2000 (Box 3:, Folder 30)
  - Caucus of Connecticut Democrats 10th Anniversary Celebration, 1979 (Box 3:, Folder 31)
  - Caucus of Connecticut Democrats 20th Anniversary Celebration, 1989 (Box 3:, Folder 32)
  - Caucus of Connecticut Democrats, A Celebration of Mims, n.d. (Box 4:, Folder 33)
  - Caucus of Connecticut Democrats, CCD Reports, 1981-1988 (Box 4:, Folder 34)
  - Connecticut District Maps, 1966 (Box 4:, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1976 (Box 4:, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1981-2002 (Box 4:, Folder 37)
  - Democratic National Committee, 1970-2000 (Box 4:, Folder 38)
  - Democratic Political Campaigns, 1968-1970 (Box 4:, Folder 39)
  - Latin America, 1984-1989 (Box 4:, Folder 40)
  - Legal Documents, 1962-1969 (Box 4:, Folder 41)
  - Legal Documents, 1970-1980 (Box 4:, Folder 42)
  - Lymes' Nuclear Freeze Arms Committee, 1981-1991 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Lymes' Nuclear Freeze Committee, 1981-1983 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Caucus of Connecticut Democrats, 1968-1970 (Box 4:, Folder 43)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Connecticut Politics, 1969-1987 (Box 5:, Folder 44)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Eugene McCarthy Presidential Campaign, 1968 (Box 5:, Folder 45)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Democratic National Convention, 1968 (Box 5:, Folder 46)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Vietnam War, 1968-1971 (Box 5:, Folder 47)
  - Newspaper Clippings, West Harford Town Council Elections, 1981-1990 (Box 5:, Folder 48)
  - Newspaper Clippings, World Conference on Women, 1995 (Box 5:, Folder 49)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Miscellaneous, 1995-2005 (Box 5:, Folder 50)
  - Nuclear Non-Proliferation (SANE, Freeze, Peace Action), 1982-2005 (Box 5:, Folder 51)
  - Tax Reform, 1969 (Box 6:, Folder 52)
  - Vietnam War, 1960-1971 (Box 6:, Folder 53)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1995 (Box 6:, Folder 54)
  - West Hartford Citizens for Peace and Justice, 1988-2010 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    Florence Woodiel, 02/17/1937-10/06/2010
  - West Hartford Town Council Resolutions, 1981-1983 (Box 6:, Folder 55)
  - West Hartford Sesquicentennial Steering Committee, 1998 (Box 6:, Folder 56)
- Series III: Photographs, 1962-2000
  - Photographs, 1962-2000 (Box 6:, Folder 57)
  - Photograph Album, 2000 (Box 6:, Folder 58)
- Series IV: Oversized, 1936-2005
  - Caucus of Connecticut Democrats Bumper Stickers, n.d. (Box 7)
  - The Chaffee School Diploma, 1936 (Box 7)
  - Connecticut College Commencement Program, 1980 (Box 7)
  - Connecticut College Archeological Seminar Nametag, 2000 (Box 7)
  - National Peace Action Coalition March on Washington Poster, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Public Utilities Control Authority Commissioner Plaque, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Public Utilities Control Authority Certificate, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Families in Crisis, Inc. Certificate of Appreciation, 04/13/1989 (Box 7)
    Butterworth, Miriam
  - Bring Our War $$$ Home!, Bumper Sticker (Box 7)
  - Ned Lamont for Governor, Bumper Sticker (Box 7)
  - State of Connecticut, General Assembly Official Citation, 04/13/2008 (Box 7)
  - The Town of West Hartford, Proclamation, 04/10/2002 (Box 7)
  - West Hartford Chamber of Commerce, 14th Annual Noah Webster Award, 04/10/2002 (Box 7)